Nishant Subramani - Aspiring Machine Learning Researcher

nishant.subramani23@gmail.com

http://github.com/hatat5

https://hatat5.github.io

Objective

I am a PhD Student in Computer Science in the Courant Institute at New York University working on machine learning and deep learning advised by Kyunghyun Cho and Sam Bowman. Currently I am working multi-task learning, neural machine translation, importance-sampling for neural language modeling, and causality.

• Research Interests: Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Multi-Task Learning, Causality, Interventional and Counterfactual Reasoning.

Education

New York University

New York, NY

PhD Computer Science focusing on Machine Learning

Sept 2017 - Present

 $\circ\,$ Advisors: Kyunghyun Cho and Sam Bowman

Northwestern University

Evanston, IL

B.A./M.S. Statistics/Computer Science; **Stat GPA:** 3.963/4.000; **MS GPA:** 4.000/4.000 Sept 2013 – June 2017

- Graduate Courses: Deep Learning, Machine Learning Foundations, Probabilistic Graphical Models, Data Mining, Adv Topics in ML, Statistical Pattern Recognition, Computational Learning Theory, Adv Topics in Bayesian Stats
- Undergrad Courses: Machine Learning, Intro to AI, Regression Analysis, Statistical Computing, Statistical Theory & Methodology I-III, Theory of Computation, Biochemistry, Cell and Molecular Biology

Publications

- 1. Subramani, Nishant, and Doug Downey. "PAG2ADMG: A Novel Methodology to Enumerate Causal Graph Structures" In 31st AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence. 2017. **Student Abstract**
- 2. Subramani, Nishant. "Identifying the Best Predictors of Unmet Health Care Needs in Children with DBD." Northwestern Undergraduate Research Journal (2015).

Research Experience

PhD Researcher in Machine Learning

New York University

PIs: Kyunghyun Cho and Sam Bowman

September 2017 – Present

- **Project 1: Working on natural language generation for machine translation, summarization, and image captioning. Deep Learning, Neural Machine Translation (NMT), LSTMs, Attention
- **Project 2: Improving pag2admg algorithm into a more efficient method to generate all Markov equivalent acyclic directed mixed graphs. Causality, Ancestral Graphs, Acyclic Directed Mixed Graphs, Markov Equivalence

Deep Learning Research Intern

Salesforce (Metamind Group)

PI: Richard Socher

March 2017 – August 2017

• **Project:** Worked on multitask learning, specifically trying to build a single system that could perform well on a myriad of NLP tasks *Deep Learning*, *MultiTask Learning*, *BiLSTMs*, *NLP*, *Meta-learning*

Research Assistant in Deep Learning & NLP

Northwestern University

PI: Doug Downey

July 2014 - March 2015; March 2016 - June 2017

- Statistics Bachelor's Thesis (Accepted to ICML 2018 Workshop on Causality): Improving my pag2admg developed at ETH Zurich into a method that generates all Markov equivalent acyclic directed mixed graphs (not necessary just ancestral) from a PAG. Causality, Ancestral Graphs, Mixed Graphs, Markov Equivalence
- Master's Thesis: Developing various methodologies to identify deep net hyperparameter settings more efficiently using active learning and sampling. Deep Learning, Hyperparameters, LSTMs, ConvNets, Active Learning
- **Project 3**: Developing various ensembling methodologies to improve state-of-the-art language model performance on the Penn Tree Bank dataset. *Deep Learning, Recurrent Neural Nets (RNNs), XGBoost*
- Project 4: Developing alternative dropout methodologies to increase variance of models from epoch to epoch to improve deep neural network performance on a variety of tasks. Deep Learning, Dropout, RNNs, ConvNets
- **Project 5**: Developed methods to input pre-existing analogical knowledge to improve word-embeddings in Google's word2vec models. *Neural Networks, Active Learning*
- Project 6** (Plan to Submit to EMNLP 2018 Workshop on Analyzing NNs for NLP): Developing methods
 to utilize importance sampling to help stochastic gradient descent convergence for neural sentence-level language modeling.
 Neural Networks, Importance Sampling, LSTMs, SGD

Research Assistant in Biomedical Informatics

Stanford University

PI: Olivier Gevaert

Jun 2015 - Jan 2016

• Project 1: Used predictive models to identify a genetic basis for cellularity in brain cancer patients using gene expression and cellular pathology data. Bayesian Networks, Structure Learning, Hierarchical Clustering

^{** -} indicates currently working on

Research Assistant in Biomedical Informatics

Feinberg School of Medicine

PI: Yuan Luo

Jan 2016 - March 2016

• **Project**: Predicted ICU 30-day readmission rates from a multivariate panel of physiological measurements using Subgraph Augmented Non-Negative Matrix Factorization (SANMF). *Non-Negative Matrix Factorization, Frequent Subgraph Mining*

Master's Semester Project Student in Systems Biology

ETH Zurich

PI: Manfred Claassen

Sept 2015 - Jan 2016

o **Project**: Developed a methodology (*The Boundary Searcher*) to efficiently calculate the r-convex hull of a point cloud in high dimensions. *R-Convex Hull, Random Walk*

Master's Semester Project Student in Statistics

ETH Zurich

PI: Marloes Maathuis

Sept 2015 – Jan 2016

• Project: Developed a novel methodology to transform a given partial ancestral graph (PAG) to the set of all ancestral acyclic directed mixed graphs that belong in the Markov equivalence class that the PAG encodes. Causality, Ancestral Graphs, Directed Graphs, Mixed Graphs

Teaching Experience

Teaching Assistant for Natural Language Understanding (Grad Course)

DSGA-1012

New York University Jan 2018 – May 2018

- o Developed homework assignments and exercises throughout the course.
- Helped advise research projects completed by students in the course that involved deep learning applied to language.

Teaching Assistant for Adv Topics in ML (Grad Seminar) EECS 395/495

Northwestern University

Jan 2017 – Mar 2017

- o Course Topic: Statistical Language Modeling focusing on Deep Learning.
- o Constructed seminar reading list, helping other students understand seminal deep NLP papers.

Teaching Assistant for Probabilistic Graphical Models (Grad Course) EECS 474

Northwestern University

Sept 2016 – Dec 2016

- $\circ~$ Helped to design course materials and structure.
- $\circ~$ Developed and graded assignments; held office hours.

Teaching Assistant for Mathematical Foundations of CS

Northwestern University

EECS 212

 $\circ~$ Helped to develop and grade assignments and exams; held office hours.

Teaching Assistant for Machine Learning

Northwestern University

EECS 349

Feb 2016 – June 2016

Sept 2016 - Dec 2016

- Devised methodology for and built a mechanical TA which uses the Vancouver crowd sourcing algorithm.
- Helped to design tree search and decision tree assignments, graded assignments, and held office hours.

Teaching Assistant for Computing Applications I & II

Northwestern University

ISP 101-1 & 101-2

Sept 2014 – March 2015

- o Co-taught course with three other teaching assistants.
- Wrote exam questions and assignments covering python and R basics.

Other Experience

Deep Learning Consultant

Talkspace

Hiring Manager: Bonnie Ray

November 2017 – August 2018

- Taught Talkspace's Data Science team about deep learning fundamentals and how to implement deep neural network models for text.
- Helped advise building and training an attention-based encoder/decoder framework as an exploratory study into the vast amounts of collected text data from therapy.

Skills

- Proficient Languages/Packages: Python, R, PyTorch
- Machine Learning Algorithms: Deep Nets (RNNs, LSTMs, CNNs), Bayesian Networks, SVMs, Logistic Regression, Decision Trees, Random Forests
- Other Computational Methods: AdaBoost, Clustering (K-means, Hierarchical), Map-Reduce

Research Presentations

• PAG2ADMG. ICML 2018, Stockholm, Sweden. Causal ML Workshop. Poster.

July 2018

• PAG2ADMG. AAAI 2017, San Francisco, CA. Student Abstract Spotlight Talk.

February 2017

• PAG2ADMG. AAAI 2017, San Francisco, CA. Student Abstract Poster.

February 2017

** - indicates currently working on

• Pag2Admg. Undergraduate Research Expo, Northwestern University. Poster.	June 2016
• The Boundary Searcher. EECS Poster Fair, Northwestern University. Poster.	Apr 2016
• Predicting Unmet Health Care Needs in Children with DBD Undergraduate Research Expo, Northwestern University. Poster.	June 2015
• Predicting Unmet Health Care Needs in Children with DBD EECS Poster Fair, Northwestern University. Poster.	Mar 2015
• How Evil are Turnovers? Undergraduate Research Expo, Northwestern University. Talk.	June 2014
• How Evil are Turnovers? Computational Statistics Conference, Northwestern University, Poster.	Apr 2014

Awards & Honors

• Henry M. MacCracken Graduate Fellowship (5 Year Fully Funded PhD Studies) 2022	September 2017 - August
$\bullet~\$500$ Conference Travel Grant from Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences	June 2018
$\bullet~\$500$ Conference Travel Grant from Weinberg College of Arts & Sciences	January 2017
• \$500 Conference Travel Grant from Undergraduate Research Northwestern Univ	versity January 2017
• Charles A & Ruby E Howell Endowed Scholarship	December 2014 - June 2017
• Academic Dean's List	September 2014 - June 2016
• Intel Science Talent Search (ISTS) Outstanding Written Report Award	March 2013
• National AP Scholar	August 2012

Students Advised

• Michael Chen - B.S. Student in Computer Science, Northwestern University	November 2016 - Present
• Gautam Srinivasan - M.S. Student in Computer Science, New York University	August 2018 - Present